MICHAEL FARES

703-244-0370 | mjfares@gmail.com

https://github.com/Michael-Fares https://michaelfares.netlify.app https://michael-fares.medium.com

FRONTEND WEB DEVELOPER | EDUCATOR

I'm a JavaScript developer with a versatile skill set in frontend / full stack technologies and best practices. I'm also an award winning educator with 10 years of university teaching experience. My goal is to use my skills to build outstanding digital learning platforms, making education truly equitable for the students of the 21st century.

Core Competencies

Frontend Development • Backend Development • Unit Testing • Agile Workflow • Relational Databases • SEO • Continuous Integration and Deployment • Web Accessibility • Curriculum Design • Educational Technology • Teaching/Higher Education • Research/Data Analysis • Fluent in Arabic

Technical Skills

HTML • CSS • Bootstrap • JavaScript • React • Redux • MaterialUI • Chart.js • Recharts.js • Node • NPM • Express • REST API • Git • Github • Google Cloud (GCP) • Heroku • Netlify • MySQL • AWS • ESLint

EXPERIENCE

Zollege, Austin, TX

Software Developer

Jan 2022 - Present

I work closely with a team of fellow developers to plan, design, build and integrate new full stack web applications and features into various digital learning platforms.

- Whiteboard and implement robust frontend user interfaces to deliver educational content to students
- Identify and collaboratively solve problems related to frontend-backend integration

University of Houston, Houston, TX

Aug 2012 - Present

Professor of Arabic

I teach Arabic as a second language to hundreds of college students from many backgrounds, and work on multiple administrative teams to deliver extracurricular offerings including community internships, study abroad, and public cultural events.

- Design, implement, and maintain original Arabic language curriculum content for all levels
- Multiple published articles and public talks on Arabic language, culture, translation and best teaching practices.
- Faculty Teaching Excellence Award, 2020
- Outstanding Mentorship Award, 2020

Greenhill School, Dallas, TX

Aug 2009 - June 2010

Middle School Teacher

- Created and taught original lesson plans for 5th graders in all subjects.
- Supervised students during after school programs and planned activities to ensure their learning and fun.
- Communicated regularly with parents about students' progress and learning needs..

EDUCATION

Austin Coding Academy Bootcamp

Full Stack Web Development | December 2021

University of Texas at Austin